<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- Make this a private "Internet Draft". -->
<?rfc private="web-server-logs"?>
<!-- Use compact format without horizontal rules between sections. -->
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<!-- Remove authorship information. -->
<?rfc authorship="no"?>
<!-- Remove index. -->
<?rfc-ext include-index="no" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY thinsp "&#8202;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY ndash "&#8211;">
  <!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
]>
<rfc xmlns:x="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext">
  <front>
    <title>Tor web server logs</title>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Purpose of this document">
      <t>BETA: As of November 8, 2017, this document is still under
      discussion and subject to change without prior notice. Feel free
      to <eref target="/about.html#contact">contact us</eref> for questions or
      concerns regarding this document.</t>
      <t>Tor's web servers, like most web servers, keep request logs for
      maintenance and informational purposes.</t>
      <t>However, unlike most other web servers, Tor's web servers use a
      privacy-aware log format that avoids logging too sensitive data about
      their users.</t>
      <t>Also unlike most other web server logs, Tor's logs are neither archived
      nor analyzed before performing a number of post-processing steps to further
      reduce any privacy-sensitive parts.</t>
      <t>This document describes 1) meta-data contained in log file names
      written by Tor's web servers, 2) the privacy-aware log format used in
      these files, and 3) subsequent sanitizing steps that are applied before
      archiving and analyzing these log files.</t>
      <t>As a basis for our current implementation this document also
      describes the naming conventions for the input log files, which is
      just a description of the current state and subject to change.</t>
      <t>As a convention for this document, all format strings conform to the
      format strings used by
      <eref
target="http://httpd.apache.org/docs/current/mod/mod_log_config.html">Apache's
mod_log_config module</eref>.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Log file metadata">
      <t>Log files have meta-data that is not part of the file's contents,
      in particular, the names of the virtual and physical hosts.</t>
      <t>All access log files written by Tor's web servers follow the naming
      convention &lt;virtual-host&gt;-access.log-YYYYMMDD, where
      "YYYYMMDD" is the date of the rotation and finalization of the log file,
      which is not used in the further sanitizing process.
      The "access.log" part serves as a marker for web server access
      logs.</t>
      <t>The virtual hostname can be inferred from the input log's name,
      whereas the physical hostname needs to be provided by other means.
      Currently, log files are made available to the santizer in a
      separate directory per physical web server host.
      Log files are typically gz-compressed,
      which is indicated by appending ".gz" to log file names, but this is
      subject to change.
      Files with unknown compression type are discarded (currently ".xz",
      ".gz", and ".bz2" are recognized).
      Overall, the sanitizer expects log files to use the following path
      format:
      <list>
        <t>&lt;physical-host&gt;/&lt;virtual-host&gt;-access.log-YYYYMMDD[.gz]</t>
      </list>
      </t>
      <t>As first safeguard against publishing log files that are too
      sensitive, we discard all files not matching the naming convention for
      access logs. This is to prevent, for example, error logs from slipping
      through.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Privacy-aware log format">
      <t>Tor's Apache web servers are configured to write log files that extend
      Apache's Combined Log Format with a couple tweaks towards privacy. For
      example, the following Apache configuration lines were in use at the time
      of writing (subject to change):
      <list>
        <t>LogFormat "0.0.0.0 - %u %{[%d/%b/%Y:00:00:00 %z]}t \"%r\" %>s %b \"%{Referer}i\" \"-\" %{Age}o" privacy</t>
        <t>LogFormat "0.0.0.1 - %u %{[%d/%b/%Y:00:00:00 %z]}t \"%r\" %>s %b \"%{Referer}i\" \"-\" %{Age}o" privacyssl</t>
        <t>LogFormat "0.0.0.2 - %u %{[%d/%b/%Y:00:00:00 %z]}t \"%r\" %>s %b \"%{Referer}i\" \"-\" %{Age}o" privacyhs</t>
      </list>
      </t>
      <t>The main difference to Apache's Common Log Format is that request IP
      addresses are removed and the field is instead used to encode whether the
      request came in via http:// (0.0.0.0), via https:// (0.0.0.1), or via the
      site's onion service (0.0.0.2).</t>
      <t>Tor's web servers are configured to use UTC as timezone, which is also
      highly recommended when rewriting request times to "00:00:00" in order for
      the subsequent sanitizing steps to work correctly. Alternatively, if the
      system timezone is not set to UTC, web servers should keep request times
      unchanged and let them be handled by the subsequent sanitizing steps.</t>
      <t>Tor's web servers are configured to rotate logs at least once per day,
      which does not necessarily happen at 00:00:00 UTC. As a result, log files
      may contain requests from up to two UTC days and several log files may
      contain requests that have been started on the same UTC day.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Sanitizing steps">
      <t>The request logs written by Tor's web servers still contain too many
      details that we are uncomfortable publishing. Therefore, we apply a couple
      of sanitizing steps on these log files before making them public and
      analyzing them ourselves. Some of these steps could as well be made
      directly by Apache, but others can only be made with a delay.</t>
      <section title="Discarding non-matching lines">
        <t>Log files are expected to contain exactly one request per line. We
        process these files line by line and discard any lines not matching the
        following criteria:
        <list>
          <t>Lines begin with Apache's Common Log Format ("%h %l %u %t \"%r\"
          %&gt;s %b") or a compatible format like one of Tor's privacy formats.
          It is acceptable if lines start with a format that is compatible to
          the Common Log Format and continue with additional fields. Those
          additional fields will later be discarded, but the line will not be
          discarded because of them.</t>
          <t>The request protocol is HTTP.</t>
          <t>The request method is either GET or HEAD.</t>
          <t>The final status of the request is neither 400 ("Bad Request") nor
          404 ("Not Found").</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>Any lines not meeting all these criteria will be discarded, and
        processing continues with the next line.</t>
        <t>In addition, log lines are treated differently according to the
        date they contain:
        <list>
        <t>During an import process the sanitizer takes all log line dates into
        account and determines the reference interval as stretching from
        the oldest date to the youngest date encountered.
        Depending on the reference interval log lines are not yet processed, if
        their date is on the edges of the reference interval, i.e., the date is
        not at least a day younger than the older endpoint or the date is only
        LIMIT days older than the younger endpoint, where LIMIT is initially set
        to two, but this might change if necessary.</t>
        <t>If the younger endpoint of the reference interval coincides with the
        current system date,  the day before is used as the new younger
        reference interval endpoint, which ensures that the sanitizer won't
        publish logs prematurely, i.e., before there is a chance that they are
        complete.  Thus, processing of log lines carrying such date is
        postponed.</t>
        <t>All log lines with dates for which the sanitizer already published
        a log file are discarded in order to avoid altering published logs.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Rewriting matching lines">
        <t>All matching lines, which are already checked to match Apache's
        Common Log Format ("%h %l %u %t \"%r\" %&gt;s %b"), are rewritten
        following these rules:
        <list>
          <t>%h: If the remote hostname starts with "0.0.0.", it is kept
          unchanged, otherwise it's rewritten to "0.0.0.0".</t>
          <t>%l: The remote logname, if present, is rewritten to "-".</t>
          <t>%u: The remote user, if present, is rewritten to "-".</t>
          <t>%t: The time the request was received is converted to UTC, unless
          the time is already given in UTC, and time and time zone components
          are rewritten to "00:00:00 +0000". Date components are kept
          unchanged.</t>
          <t>%r: If the first line of request contains a query string, that
          query string is removed from "?" to the end of the request string.
          Otherwise the first line of request is kept unchanged.</t>
          <t>%&gt;s: The final status is kept unchanged.</t>
          <t>%b: The size of response in bytes is kept unchanged.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>Any columns exceeding Apache's Common Log Format are discarded.</t>
        <t>The result is still supposed to be fully compatible with the Common
        Log Format and can be processed by any tools being capable of processing
        that format.</t>
      </section>
      <section title="Re-assembling log files">
        <t>Rewritten log lines are re-assembled into sanitized log files based
        on physical host, virtual host, and request start date.</t>
        <t>The naming convention for sanitized log files is:
        <list>
          <t>&lt;virtual-host&gt;_&lt;physical-host&gt;_access.log_YYYYMMDD[.xz]</t>
        </list>
        The underscore is a separator symbol between the various parts of
        the filename.
        </t>
        <t>Sanitized log files may additionally be sorted into directories by
        virtual host and date as in:
        <list>
          <t>&lt;virtual-host&gt;/YYYY/MM/&lt;virtual-host&gt;_&lt;physical-host&gt;_access.log_YYYYMMDD[.xz]</t>
        </list>
        The virtual hostnames, like 'metrics.torproject.org' or
        'dist.torproject.org', are more familiar to the public and were therefore
        chosen to be the first naming component.
        </t>
        <t>As last and certainly not least important sanitizing step, all
        rewritten log lines are sorted alphabetically, so that request order
        cannot be inferred from sanitized log files.</t>
        <t>Sanitized log files are typically compressed before publication. In
        particular the sorting step allows for highly efficient compression
        rates. We typically use XZ for compression, which is indicated by
        appending ".xz" to log file names, but this is subject to change.</t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back/>
</rfc>

