<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- Make this a private "Internet Draft". -->
<?rfc private="sanitized-bridge-descriptors"?>
<!-- Use compact format without horizontal rules between sections. -->
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<!-- Remove authorship information. -->
<?rfc authorship="no"?>
<!-- Remove index. -->
<?rfc-ext include-index="no" ?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY nbsp "&#160;">
  <!ENTITY thinsp "&#8202;">
  <!ENTITY nbhy "&#8209;">
  <!ENTITY ndash "&#8211;">
  <!ENTITY mdash "&#8212;">
]>
<rfc xmlns:x="http://purl.org/net/xml2rfc/ext">
  <front>
    <title>Tor bridge descriptors</title>
  </front>
  <middle>
    <section title="Purpose of this document">
      <t>Bridges and the bridge authority publish bridge descriptors that are
      used by censored clients to connect to the network.
      We aim for publishing all network directory data for informational and
      statistical purposes.
      We cannot, however, make bridge descriptors publicly available in the same
      way as we publish relay descriptors, because that would defeat the purpose
      of making bridges hard to enumerate for censors.
      We therefore sanitize bridge descriptors by removing all potentially
      identifying information and then publish sanitized versions.</t>
      <t>The purpose of this document is to specify the document format of
      sanitized bridge descriptors.
      These descriptors are based on original, non-sanitized bridge descriptors
      after sanitizing any parts that would make it easier to enumerate
      bridges.
      Unless stated otherwise, the
      <eref target="https://gitweb.torproject.org/torspec.git/tree/dir-spec.txt#n193">
      document meta-format</eref> of the Tor directory protocol, version 3
      is used.</t>
    </section>
    <section title="Changes">
      <t>Sanitization has changed several times over the years.
      The following list contains all major changes that resulted in raising the
      "@type" annotation of a descriptor:
        <list>
          <t>May 30, 2012: "@type" annotations were first added to sanitized
          descriptors to indicate descriptor type and version: "@type
          bridge-server-descriptor 1.0", "@type bridge-extra-info 1.0", and
          "@type bridge-network-status 1.0".</t>
          <t>June 29, 2012: "@type bridge-extra-info 1.1" added sanitized
          "transport" lines.</t>
          <t>February 1, 2013: "@type bridge-extra-info 1.2" was supposed to
          indicate added "ntor-onion-key" lines, but those changes only affected
          bridge server descriptors, not extra-info descriptors. So, nothing has
          changed as compared to "@type bridge-extra-info 1.1", and there may be
          "@type bridge-server-descriptor 1.0" descriptors with and without
          those lines.</t>
          <t>June 19, 2015: "@type bridge-server-descriptor 1.1" and "@type
          bridge-extra-info 1.3" added "master-key-ed25519" and
          "router-digest-sha256" lines to descriptors published by bridges using
          an ed25519 master key.</t>
          <t>September 18, 2016: "@type bridge-server-descriptor 1.2" and "@type
          bridge-network-status 1.1" introduced sanitized TCP ports.</t>
          <t>July 10, 2017: "@type bridge-network-status 1.2" introduced the
          "fingerprint" line, containing the fingerprint of the bridge authority
          which produced the document, to the header. </t>
        </list>
      </t>
    </section>
    <section title="Sanitizing potentially sensitive descriptor items">
      <t>The following sanitizing steps are applied to original, non-sanitized
      bridge descriptors.</t>
      <section anchor="type-annotation" title="Prefix with @type annotation">
        <t>"@type" SP DescriptorType SP Version
        <list>
          <t>DescriptorType is a fixed string that identifies the sanitized
          bridge descriptor type.
          Known strings are listed in the sections below.</t>
          <t>Version is set by the sanitizer to indicate changes in the
          sanitizing process.
          The version string consist of a major version number for
          backward-incompatible changes and a minor version number for
          backward-compatible changes.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="fingerprint" title="Replace RSA fingerprints">
        <t>HashedFingerprint = SHA1(Fingerprint)
        <list>
          <t>Fingerprint is the decoded binary representation of the SHA-1
          hash of an ASN.1 encoded RSA public key.</t>
          <t>The (non-sanitized) Fingerprint of a bridge could, in theory, be
          used quite easily to uniquely identify the bridge.
          However, clients can request a bridge's current descriptor by
          sending its Fingerprint to the bridge authority.
          This is a feature to make bridges on dynamic IP addresses more
          useful, but it would also allow for trivial enumeration of bridges.
          Therefore, the original Fingerprint (and anything that could be used
          to derive it) is removed from descriptors and replaced with
          something else that can be used to uniquely identify the bridge.
          The approach taken here is to replace the Fingerprint with its SHA-1
          hash.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="master-key-ed25519" title="Replace ed25519 master keys">
        <t>HashedMasterKeyEd25519 = SHA256(MasterKeyEd25519)
        <list>
          <t>MasterKeyEd25519 is the decoded binary representation of an
          ed25519 master key.</t>
          <t>Similar to (non-sanitized) <xref target="fingerprint">RSA
          fingerprints</xref>, ed25519 master keys could be used to uniquely
          identify bridges and to request a current descriptor from the
          bridge authority.
          That is why they are replaced with their SHA-256 hashes.
          In cases where a descriptor only contains an ed25519 certificate and
          no ed25519 master key, the (non-sanitized) master key is first
          extracted from the certificate before sanitizing it.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="crypto"
               title="Remove public keys, certificates, and signatures">
        <t>[Removed.]
        <list>
          <t>Some of the public keys and certificates could be used to derive
          key fingerprints, hence they need to be replaced or removed.
          However, replacing them seemed unnecessary and overly complex with
          respect to keeping state on the sanitizing host.
          That is why most public keys, certificates, and signatures are
          simply removed in the sanitizing process.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="ipv4-address" title="Replace IPv4 addresses">
        <t>SanitizedIpv4Address = "10." | KeyedHash</t>
        <t>KeyedHash = SHA256(Ipv4Address | Fingerprint | Secret)[:3]
        <list>
          <t>Address is the 4-byte long binary representation of the
          (non-sanitized) IPv4 address.</t>
          <t>Fingerprint is the 20-byte long binary representation of the
          (non-sanitized) long-term identity fingerprint.</t>
          <t>Secret is a 31-byte long secure random string that changes once
          per month for all descriptors and statuses published in that
          month.</t>
          <t>The [:3] operator picks the first three bytes from the left of the
          result and encodes it as three dot-separated decimal numbers.
          </t>
          <t>Sanitizing IPv4 addresses is obviously required to prevent
          enumeration of bridges.
          The approach taken is here is to replace IPv4 addresses with
          syntactical valid addresses in the private IPv4 address space 10/8
          based on a keyed hash function that produces the same sanitized
          address for a given bridge, IPv4 address, and month.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="ipv6-address" title="Replace IPv6 addresses">
        <t>SanitizedIpv6Address = "[fd9f:2e19:3bcf::" | KeyedHash | "]"</t>
        <t>KeyedHash = SHA256(Ipv6Address | Fingerprint | Secret)[:3]
        <list>
          <t>Address is the 16-byte long binary representation of the
          (non-sanitized) IPv6 address.</t>
          <t>Fingerprint is the 20-byte long binary representation of the
          (non-sanitized) long-term identity fingerprint.</t>
          <t>Secret is a 19-byte long secure random string that changes once
          per month for all descriptors and statuses published in that
          month.</t>
          <t>The [:3] operator picks the first three bytes from the left of the
          result and encodes it as two lower-case hexadecimal numbers, a
          colon, and another four lower-case hexadecimal numbers.
          </t>
          <t>Similar to <xref target="ipv4-address">IPv4 addresses</xref>,
          IPv6 addresses are replaced with syntactical valid addresses in the
          address range [fd9f:2e19:3bcf::/116] based on a keyed hash function
          that produces the same sanitized address for a given bridge, IPv6
          address, and month.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="tcp-port" title="Replace TCP ports">
        <t>SanitizedPort = KeyedHash / 2^2 + 2^15 + 2^14</t>
        <t>KeyedHash = SHA256(Port | Fingerprint | Secret)[:2]
        <list>
          <t>Port is the 2-byte long binary representation of the TCP
          port.</t>
          <t>Fingerprint is the 20-byte long binary representation of the
          bridge's long-term identity fingerprint.</t>
          <t>Secret is a 33-byte long secure random string that changes once
          per month for all descriptors and statuses published in that
          month.</t>
          <t>The [:2] operator means that we pick the first two bytes from the
          left of the result, and the /, ^, and + operators are all integer
          operators.
          </t>
          <t>TCP ports that are 0 in the original are left unchanged.</t>
          <t>It may be less obvious that TCP ports need to be sanitized, but an
          unusual TCP port used by a high-value bridge might still stand out and
          provide yet another way to locate and block the bridge.
          Therefore, each non-zero TCP port is replaced with a port number in
          the range from 49152 to 65535, which is reserved for private services,
          based on a keyed hash function that produces the same sanitized port
          for a given bridge, TCP port, and month.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="contact" title="Remove contact information">
        <t>SanitizedContact = "somebody"
        <list>
          <t>If there is contact information in a descriptor, it is replaced by
          the constant string "somebody".
          (Note that this sanitizing step is subject to change and maybe be
          changed in a future version towards retaining the original contact
          information.)</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="transport"
               title="Remove extraneous transport information">
        <t>[Removed.]
        <list>
          <t>Bridges may provide transports in addition to the OR protocol and
          include information about these transports for the bridge
          distribution service.
          In that case, any IP addresses, TCP ports, or additional arguments
          are removed, only leaving in the supported transport names.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="replaced-digest"
               title="Replace digests in referencing descriptors">
        <t>SanitizedSha1Digest = SHA1(Sha1Digest)</t>
        <t>SanitizedSha256Digest = SHA256(Sha256Digest)
        <list>
          <t>Sha1Digest is the 20-byte long binary representation of a
          descriptor's SHA-1 digest.</t>
          <t>Sha256Digest is the 32-byte long binary representation of a
          descriptor's SHA-256 digest.</t>
          <t>Some descriptors reference other descriptors by their digest.
          However, these digests are also somewhat sensitive, because it
          shouldn't be possible to reconstruct the original descriptor with
          help of these digests.
          That is why digests in referencing descriptors are replaced with
          either the hex-encoded SHA-1 hash or the base64-encoded SHA-256 hash
          of the original digest, depending on which hash algorithm was used
          to generate the original digest.
          The resulting digest string in a referencing descriptor can then be
          matched to an <xref target="appended-digest">appended digest</xref>
          in a referenced descriptor.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section anchor="appended-digest"
               title="Append digests to referenced descriptors">
        <t>SanitizedSha1Digest = SHA1(Sha1Digest)</t>
        <t>SanitizedSha256Digest = SHA256(Sha256Digest)
        <list>
          <t>Sha1Digest is the 20-byte long binary representation of a
          descriptor's SHA-1 digest.</t>
          <t>Sha256Digest is the 32-byte long binary representation of a
          descriptor's SHA-256 digest.</t>
          <t>As stated <xref target="replaced-digest">above</xref>, some
          descriptors are referenced by others by their digest.
          But in contrast to non-sanitized descriptors, it's neither possible
          to compute the digest of a sanitized descriptor nor is it desirable
          to include the original digest.
          The reason is that it shouldn't be possible to reconstruct the
          original descriptor with help of the original digest.
          That is why descriptors that are typically referenced from others
          may contain additional lines with the hex-encoded SHA-1 hash or the
          base64-encoded SHA-256 hash of the original digest, depending on
          which hash algorithm would have been used to generate the original
          digest.
          The resulting digest string can then be matched to a 
          <xref target="replaced-digest">sanitized digest</xref> in a
          referencing descriptor.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Server descriptor document format">
      <t>The document format of sanitized bridge server descriptors resembles
      the document format of (non-sanitized) server descriptors as much as
      possible.
      Also refer to the
      <eref target="https://gitweb.torproject.org/torspec.git/tree/dir-spec.txt">
      Tor directory protocol, version 3 specification</eref>, as the following
      sections only specify items that differ from their non-sanitized counterparts.</t>
      <section title="Annotations">
        <t>The bridge authority may prefix descriptors with one or more
        annotation lines containing metadata, and the sanitizer may add
        annotation lines with metadata about the sanitizing process.</t>
        <t>"@purpose" SP Purpose NL
        <list>
          <t>[Removed.]</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"@type" SP "bridge-server-descriptor" SP Version
        <list>
          <t>[Exactly once.]</t>
          <t>Version can be one of the following numbers:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>"1.0" was the first version.
            There was supposed to be a newer version indicating added
            "ntor-onion-key" lines, but due to a mistake only the version
            number of sanitized bridge extra-info descriptors was raised.
            As a result, there may be sanitized bridge server descriptors
            with version 1.0 with and without those lines.</t>
            <t>"1.1" added "master-key-ed25519" and "router-digest-sha256"
            lines to server descriptors published by bridges using an
            ed25519 master key.</t>
            <t>"1.2" introduced sanitized TCP ports.</t>
          </list>
          </t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Descriptor body">
        <t>The body of a sanitized bridge server descriptor contains several
        sanitized items as specified in the following:</t>
        <t>"router" SP Nickname SP SanitizedAddress SP SanitizedORPort SP
        SOCKSPort SP SanitizedDirPort NL
        <list>
          <t>[At start, exactly once.]</t>
          <t>Nickname is the bridge's original, unchanged nickname.</t>
          <t>SanitizedAddress is the bridge's
          <xref target="ipv4-address">sanitized IP address</xref>.</t>
          <t>SanitizedORPort is the bridge's
          <xref target="tcp-port">sanitized OR port</xref> (since version 1.2)
          or the original OR port (until version 1.1).</t>
          <t>SOCKSPort is deprecated and always 0, as in the original,
          non-sanitized server descriptor.</t>
          <t>SanitizedDirPort is the bridge's
          <xref target="tcp-port">sanitized directory port</xref> (since
          version 1.2) or the original directory port (until version 1.1).</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"or-address" SP SanitizedAddress ":" SanitizedPort NL
        <list>
          <t>[Any number.]</t>
          <t>SanitizedAddress is either an additional
          <xref target="ipv4-address">sanitized IPv4 address</xref> or
          <xref target="ipv6-address">sanitized IPv6 address</xref>.</t>
          <t>SanitizedPort is an additional
          <xref target="tcp-port">sanitized OR port</xref> (since version 1.2)
          or original OR port (until version 1.1).</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"identity-ed25519" NL CertificateBlock NL
        <list>
          <t>[Removed.]</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"master-key-ed25519" SP SanitizedMasterKey NL
        <list>
          <t>[At most once.]</t>
          <t>SanitizedMasterKey is the bridge's
          <xref target="master-key-ed25519">sanitized ed25519 master
          key</xref>.
          (Introduced in version 1.1, not present in earlier versions.)</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"fingerprint" SP SanitizedFingerprint NL
        <list>
          <t>[At most once.]</t>
          <t>SanitizedFingerprint is the bridge's
          <xref target="fingerprint">sanitized fingerprint</xref>, formatted
          with a single SP after every 4 characters.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"contact" SP SanitizedContact NL
        <list>
          <t>[At most once.]</t>
          <t>SanitizedContact is the bridge's <xref target="contact">sanitized
          contact information</xref>.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"reject" SP ExitPattern NL
        <list>
          <t>[Any number.]</t>
          <t>ExitPattern contains the bridge's
          <xref target="ipv4-address">sanitized IPv4 address</xref>, if the
          original line contained the bridge's primary IP address, and is
          otherwise unchanged.
          (Note that "accept" lines are exempt from this sanitizing step,
          which doesn't really make sense and which might change in the
          future.)</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"extra-info-digest" SP SanitizedSha1Digest [SP
        SanitizedSha256Digest] NL
        <list>
          <t>[At most once.]</t>
          <t>SanitizedSha1Digest is the
          <xref target="replaced-digest">sanitized SHA-1 digest</xref> of the
          corresponding extra-info descriptor.</t>
          <t>SanitizedSha256Digest is the
          <xref target="replaced-digest">sanitized SHA-256 digest</xref> of
          corresponding extra-info descriptor and is only included if the
          original line contained a SHA-256 digest.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"family" (SP Name)* NL
        <list>
          <t>[At most once.]</t>
          <t>Name is either the <xref target="fingerprint">sanitized
          fingerprint</xref> or unchanged nickname of another relay or bridge
          that is purportedly in the same family as this bridge.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"onion-key" NL PublicKeyBlock NL
        <list>
          <t>[Removed.]</t>
          <t>The bridge's medium-term RSA key is removed together with most other
          <xref target="crypto">public keys, certificates, and
          signatures</xref>.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"signing-key" NL PublicKeyBlock NL
        <list>
          <t>[Removed.]</t>
          <t>The bridge's long-term RSA key is removed together with most other
          <xref target="crypto">public keys, certificates, and
          signatures</xref>.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"onion-key-crosscert" NL SignatureBlock NL
        <list>
          <t>[Removed.]</t>
          <t>This cross signature created with the onion-key is removed together
          with most other <xref target="crypto">public keys, certificates, and
          signatures</xref>.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"ntor-onion-key-crosscert" SP PublicKey NL
        <list>
          <t>[Removed.]</t>
          <t>This cross signature created with the ntor-onion-key is removed
          together with most other <xref target="crypto">public keys,
          certificates, and signatures</xref>.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"ntor-onion-key" SP NtorOnionKey NL
        <list>
          <t>[At most once.]</t>
          <t>The curve25519 public key used for the ntor circuit extended
          handshake is included without modification in most sanitized
          descriptors.
          This key was originally missing in version 1.0, and there was
          supposed to be a newer version indicating added "ntor-onion-key"
          lines.
          But due to a mistake only the version number of sanitized bridge
          extra-info descriptors was raised.
          As a result, there are sanitized bridge server descriptors with
          version 1.0 with and without this line.
          All subsequent versions contain this line</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"router-sig-ed25519" SP Signature NL
        <list>
          <t>[Removed.]</t>
          <t>The ed25519 signature is removed together with most other
          <xref target="crypto">public keys, certificates, and
          signatures</xref>.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"router-signature" NL SignatureBlock NL
        <list>
          <t>[Removed.]</t>
          <t>The RSA signature is removed together with most other
          <xref target="crypto">public keys, certificates, and
          signatures</xref>.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"router-digest-sha256" SP SanitizedSha256Digest NL
        <list>
          <t>[At most once.]</t>
          <t>SanitizedSha256Digest is the
          <xref target="appended-digest">sanitized SHA-256 digest</xref> of
          this descriptor and is only included if the original descriptor
          contained an ed25519 signature of the descriptor's SHA-256 digest.
          (Introduced in version 1.1, not present in earlier versions.)</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"router-digest" SP SanitizedSha1Digest NL
        <list>
          <t>[At end, exactly once.]</t>
          <t>SanitizedSha1Digest is the
          <xref target="appended-digest">sanitized SHA-1 digest</xref> of
          this descriptor.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Extra-info descriptor document format">
      <t>The document format of sanitized extra-info descriptors follows the
      same approach as sanitized server descriptors by changing as few items as
      possible in their original, non-sanitized counterpart.
      The original format is specified in the
      <eref target="https://gitweb.torproject.org/torspec.git/tree/dir-spec.txt">Tor
      directory protocol, version 3</eref>.
      Only the changes to that specification are listed below.</t>
      <section title="Annotations">
        <t>"@type" SP "bridge-extra-info" SP Version
        <list>
          <t>[Exactly once.]</t>
          <t>Version can be one of the following numbers:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>"1.0" was the first version.</t>
            <t>"1.1" added sanitized "transport" lines.</t>
            <t>"1.2" was supposed to indicate added "ntor-onion-key" lines,
            but those changes only affected bridge server descriptors, not
            extra-info descriptors.
            So, nothing has changed as compared to version 1.1.</t>
            <t>"1.3" added "master-key-ed25519" and "router-digest-sha256"
            lines to extra-info descriptors published by bridges using an
            ed25519 master key.</t>
          </list>
          </t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Descriptor body">
        <t>Several items in the extra-info descriptor body are changed or
        removed as compared to original, non-sanitized descriptors:</t>
        <t>"extra-info" SP Nickname SP SanitizedFingerprint NL
        <list>
          <t>[At start, exactly once.]</t>
          <t>Nickname is the bridge's original, unchanged nickname.</t>
          <t>SanitizedFingerprint is the bridge's
          <xref target="fingerprint">sanitized fingerprint</xref>.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"transport" SP TransportName NL
        <list>
          <t>[Any number.]</t>
          <t>TransportName is the transport name as found in the original
          line.</t>
          <t>Any further details about this
          <xref target="transport">transport</xref>, including any IP
          addresses, TCP ports, or additional arguments are removed, only
          leaving in the supported transport names.
          (Introduced in version 1.1, not present in earlier versions.)</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"transport-info SP TransportInfo NL
        <list>
          <t>[Removed.]</t>
          <t>Any lines containing <xref target="transport">extraneous transport
          information</xref> are removed.
          (Note that these lines are not even specified for original,
          non-sanitized descriptors.)</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"identity-ed25519" NL CertificateBlock NL
        <list>
          <t>[Removed.]</t>
          <t>The RSA signature is removed together with most other
          <xref target="crypto">public keys, certificates, and
          signatures</xref>.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"master-key-ed25519" SP SanitizedMasterKey NL
        <list>
          <t>[At most once.]</t>
          <t>SanitizedMasterKey is the bridge's
          <xref target="master-key-ed25519">sanitized ed25519 master
          key</xref>.
          (Introduced in version 1.3, not present in earlier versions.)</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"router-sig-ed25519" SP Signature NL
        <list>
          <t>[Removed.]</t>
          <t>The ed25519 signature is removed together with most other
          <xref target="crypto">public keys, certificates, and
          signatures</xref>.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"router-signature" NL SignatureBlock NL
        <list>
          <t>[Removed.]</t>
          <t>The RSA signature is removed together with most other
          <xref target="crypto">public keys, certificates, and
          signatures</xref>.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"router-digest-sha256" SP SanitizedSha256Digest NL
        <list>
          <t>[At most once.]</t>
          <t>SanitizedSha256Digest is the
          <xref target="appended-digest">sanitized SHA-256 digest</xref> of
          this descriptor and is only included if the original descriptor
          contained an ed25519 signature of the descriptor's SHA-256 digest.
          (Introduced in version 1.3, not present in earlier versions.)</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"router-digest" SP SanitizedSha1Digest NL
        <list>
          <t>[At end, exactly once.]</t>
          <t>SanitizedSha1Digest is the
          <xref target="appended-digest">sanitized SHA-1 digest</xref> of
          this descriptor.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section title="Network status document format">
      <t>The document format of bridge network statuses is loosely based on the
      network status format specified in the
      <eref target="https://gitweb.torproject.org/torspec.git/tree/attic/dir-spec-v2.txt">Tor
      directory protocol, version 2</eref>.
      However, the preamble of bridge network statuses contains far fewer items
      than that of (relay) network statuses, and the ones that are similar
      differ in some of the details.
      That's why all preamble lines that exist in sanitized bridge network
      statuses are specified below, not just the ones that differ.</t>
      <section title="Annotations">
        <t>Sanitized bridge network statuses start with one or more
        annotations:</t>
        <t>"@type" SP "bridge-network-status" SP Version NL
        <list>
          <t>[Exactly once.]</t>
          <t>Version can be one of the following numbers:
          <list style="symbols">
            <t>"1.0" was the first version.</t>
            <t>"1.1" introduced sanitized TCP ports.</t>
            <t>"1.2" introduced the "fingerprint" line, containing the
            fingerprint of the bridge authority which produced the document,
            to the header.</t>
          </list>
          </t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Preamble">
        <t>The preamble contains zero or more of the following items in no
        predefined order:</t>
        <t>"published" SP Publication NL
        <list>
          <t>[Exactly once.]</t>
          <t>Publication is the publication time for this document, which is
          left unchanged in the sanitizing process.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"flag-thresholds" SP Thresholds NL
        <list>
          <t>[At most once.]</t>
          <t>Thresholds are internal performance thresholds that the bridge
          directory authority had at the moment it was forming a status, which
          are left unchanged in the sanitizing process.
          This item was first introduced in
          <eref target="https://gitweb.torproject.org/torspec.git/tree/dir-spec.txt">Tor
          directory protocol, version 3</eref>.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"fingerprint" SP Fingerprint NL;
        <list>
          <t>[At most once.]</t>
          <t>Fingerprint is the (non-sanitized) SHA-1 hash of the bridge
          authority's long-term signing key, encoded as 40 upper-case
          hexadecimal characters, which is either added or left unchanged in
          the sanitizing process.
          (Introduced in version 1.2, not present in earlier versions.)</t>
        </list>
        </t>
      </section>
      <section title="Router entries">
        <t>For each bridge, there is one router entry containing one or more
        items.
        Similar to the preamble specification, the following specification
        lists all lines known in sanitized bridge network statuses, including
        those that are left unchanged in the sanitizing process.</t>
        <t>"r" SP Nickname SP SanitizedFingerprint SP SanitizedSha1Digest SP
        Publication SP SanitizedAddress SP SanitizedORPort SP SanitizedDirPort
        NL
        <list>
          <t>[At start, exactly once.]</t>
          <t>Nickname is the bridge's original, unchanged nickname.</t>
          <t>SanitizedFingerprint is the bridge's
          <xref target="fingerprint">sanitized fingerprint</xref>.</t>
          <t>SanitizedSha1Digest is the
          <xref target="replaced-digest">sanitized SHA-1 digest</xref> of
          the corresponding server descriptor.</t>
          <t>Publication is the publication time for the corresponding
          server descriptor, which is left unchanged in the sanitizing
          process.</t>
          <t>SanitizedAddress is the bridge's
          <xref target="ipv4-address">sanitized IP address</xref>.</t>
          <t>SanitizedORPort is the bridge's
          <xref target="tcp-port">sanitized OR port</xref> (since version 1.1)
          or the original OR port (until version 1.0).</t>
          <t>SanitizedDirPort is the bridge's
          <xref target="tcp-port">sanitized directory port</xref> (since
          version 1.1) or the original directory port (until version 1.0).</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"a" SP SanitizedAddress ":" SanitizedPort NL
        <list>
          <t>[Any number.]</t>
          <t>SanitizedAddress is either an additional
          <xref target="ipv4-address">sanitized IPv4 address</xref> or
          <xref target="ipv6-address">sanitized IPv6 address</xref>.</t>
          <t>SanitizedPort is an additional <xref target="tcp-port">sanitized
          OR port</xref>.</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"s" ... NL
        <list>
          <t>[Unchanged.]</t>
        </list>
        </t>
        <t>"w" ... NL
        <list>
          <t>[Unchanged.]</t>
          </list>
        </t>
        <t>"p" ... NL
          <list>
            <t>[Unchanged.]</t>
          </list>
        </t>
      </section>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back/>
</rfc>

